Finding Aid for The American Hotel and Al's Bar Project records LSC.2305
UCLA Library Special Collections
The American Hotel and Al's Bar Project records
1976-2004
1979-2001
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kreisel, Rachel
Kreisel, Marc
LSC.2305
19.7 linear feet (14 document boxes, 5 shoe boxes, 5 flat oversize boxes, 3 half document boxes, 2 no compromise boxes, 1 slide box, 1 flat box, 1 oversize disparate box and 1 map folder)
The American Hotel and Al's Bar Project was a grassroots creative complex on the corner of Hewitt Street and Traction Avenue in downtown Los Angeles. Conceptual artist Marc Kreisel designed the project as a work of functional sculpture to circulate money and creative support back into the community. The collection spans from 1976-2004 and consists of flyers, posters, photographs, correspondence, scripts, Rolodexes, calendars, theater programs, press releases, financial records, and bar memorabilia such as the cash can, the jukebox records, the beer taps, t-shirts, signs, and a microphone.
Conditions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9978585733606533
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marc and Rachel Kreisel, 2015.
Biography/History
In 1979, conceptual artist Marc Kreisel and three partners closed escrow on a building on the corner of Hewitt Street and Traction Avenue in downtown L.A. Kreisel envisioned The American Hotel and Al's Bar as elements of a grassroots creative complex; a work of functional sculpture that was rooted in Joseph Beuys' Honey Pump. What Kreisel called the "Money Pump" was designed as a means to circulate money and creative support back into the community. "It was a capitalistic endeavor to support the arts by itself—an alternative to the feds and the state and getting grants." ("Marc: My Words" L.A. Weekly, July 5, 1985)
The residential hotel upstairs and the bar downstairs would become a self-sustaining entity by and for artists. The hotel provided cheap housing for artists new to the area. Ten rooms were set aside for the American Gallery which showed works by local artists. Profits from the bar often went to purchasing art. But it soon became apparent that the art community alone could not sustain the bar. Kreisel agreed to let two tenants in the hotel book bands. By 1980 a newly energized music scene was emerging in L.A. Kreisel's laissez faire management philosophy allowed a succession of bookers free reign to showcase bands that were too unknown to play the larger Hollywood clubs, bands like Nirvana, Sonic Youth, Beck, Social Distortion and Fear built their audiences by playing Al's. "It's nearly impossible to overestimate the importance of the club to unsigned and risk-taking bands." (Jim Freak, L.A. Reader, March/April 1999)
Local writers and actors approached Kreisel, and together they established the one non-profit entity of the complex, Al's National Theatre, which produced dozens of original works. "We had a policy back when I first opened where I would let people go to their emotional limits," recalled Kreisel. ("The Goal at Al's Bar Is to Circulate Money" The Reader, October 25, 1989)
The purpose was never gentrification. Kreisel intentionally retained the original uses of the building, i.e. the bar and the hotel. Al's Bar and the American Hotel were intended, as Christopher Knight once noted, to realize "art as a verb."
Scope and Content
The American Hotel and Al's Bar Project records range in date from 1976-2004. The collection consists of flyers, posters, photographs, correspondence, scripts, Rolodexes, calendars, theater programs, press releases, financial records, and bar memorabilia such as the cash can, the jukebox records, the beer taps, t-shirts, signs, and a microphone.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
1. Programming materials
2. Publicity materials
3. Correspondence
4. Financial records
5. Memorabilia
Related Material
S.A. Griffin collection of underground poetry, Scott Wannberg, and The Carma Bums, circa 1950-2015 (Collection 2248). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Punk zines and ephemera collection, 1977-2015 (Collection 2276). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Razorcake/Gorsky Press, Inc. records, 1989-2016 (Collection 2284). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Darby Romeo collection of zines, 1987- (Collection 1746). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Art, American -- California -- Los Angeles -- 20th century.; Punk culture and art -- United States; Experimental theater.; Alternative rock music -- California -- Los Angeles; Nightclubs -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives; Bars (Drinking establishments) -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Alternative spaces (Arts facilities) -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives; American Hotel and Al's Bar Project -- Archives
- Programming materials, 1976-2001
  Scope and Content
  Programming materials include calendars, phone lists, schedules, procedures, programs, scripts, photographs, and ephemera.
  - Marc Kreisel bio (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Artist biography for Marc Kreisel, the sole proprietor of Al's Bar who held the master lease to the American Hotel. The folder also contains six G.L. Porter exhibition books given to Kreisel, one of which is number 4 of 26 printed and signed by Porter.
  - Kreisel's calendars, 1993, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    Scope and Contents
    Marc Kreisel's calendars contain names of artists, phone numbers, notes and appointments concerning the American Hotel, Al's Bar, Al's National Theater, and the American Gallery.
  - Kreisel's telephone book, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Marc Kreisel's personal telephone book filled with contact names, phone numbers, and notes.
  - Kreisel's notebook (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Notebook contains Marc Kreisel's artist statement, designs for the bar layout, to-do lists, phone numbers, his alternative vision of financial support for The American Hotel and Al's Bar Project which he calls the "Money Pump," and finally, his "Al's Bar Will Never Rest In Peace" tombstone sketches.
  - Kreisel's artist statement (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Marc Kreisel's statement is divided into the following sections: Profit vs. Non-Profit, Real Estate/The American Hotel, and Retail Sales/Al's Bar. Within the Al's Bar portion, Kreisel states, "Plunging toilets was not my first choice of careers but if you do a task long enough you become good at it. After 22 years I consider myself an expert."
  - Functionists High catalogue, 1990 May 20-June 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    This catalogue documents an American Gallery group exhibition curated by Marc Kreisel and Katy Crowe. This publication features an essay by Peter Plagens and includes biographies of the following artists: Hans Burkhardt, Connor Everts, Claire Falkenstein, James Jarvaise, Ynez Johnston, Matsumi Kanemitsu, Helen Lundeberg, Emerson Woelffer, and June Wayne.
  - LA Boiler Works Steam Show booklet, 1987 July 4 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    This booklet documents a show which was connected to the American Gallery and sponsored by Al's Bar.
  - American Gallery ephemera (Box 1, Folder 8)
    One business card for Jett Jackson, a downtown artist who was in three American Gallery group shows between 1989 and 1992.
  - History of Al's Bar (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Biography/History
    Rachel Kreisel shares more details about a week long American Hotel party which featured sleepless nights and 5 gallon Arrowhead water jugs full of alcohol, "The party in the hotel was tossed by a guy named Gregory Dimit. It was a one off affair, but well remembered nonetheless."
    Kreisel also recalls an infamous bar party, "The Theorectical was maybe 4 or 5 times in the bar by Jack Marquette. Those were pretty rowdy gay guy parties, some ACT UP LA and others, that scared the bejeezus out of the bar manager who had thought, 'Oh, a gay guy party. That'll be nice and sedate.'"
    Marc Kreisel's handwritten notes and timelines concerning the origins of The American Hotel and Al's Bar Project. According to Marc, "The whole idea of Al's Bar, no matter what the Punks say, and as it turns out The American Hotel as well, was to support an art gallery." This folder includes writing by Rachel Kreisel concerning The American Hotel, Al's Bar, and the American Gallery. Rachel describes Barbara T. Smith's 1980 "Public Spirit" performance, Piercing the Corporate Veil at The American Hotel, the American Gallery's "biggest show" in which Dustin Shuler pinned a 700 pound aircraft to the side of The American Hotel with a twenty foot nail, and raucous parties at the hotel and the bar.
  - The Al's Bar Handbook (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Handbook includes chapter headings and contents such as the "Money Pump" for Al's Bar, the American Gallery, and Al's National Theater. Chapter headings are often followed by anecdotes such as the following: "Some times we had as many as 6 people on line at one time. Mostly lesbian chicks since at that time Al's had definitely gone Lesbo."
  - Al's Bar employee schedule (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Employee schedule includes hours of operation, standard set times, employee names, assignments, and a bartender contact list.
  - Al's Bar phone lists (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Lists include numbers for Marc and Rachel, bookers, bartenders, soundmen, beer vendors, banks, and machines.
  - Band playlist (Box 1, Folder 13)
    One blank playlist includes lines for the band name and set list.
  - SST Records guest list, 1994 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Guest list for The Leaving Trains show at Al's Bar.
  - Musician releases, 1995 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Musician releases for the Live At Al's compilation include band play lists and band sign-in sheets.
  - Al's Bar calendar masters, 1996-2001 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Photocopied calendars document monthly programming and include cut and paste originals.
  - ZOO TV production booklet, 1996 May 6-17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Al's Bar movie materials, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
    Folders contain a proposal, scripts, notes, invoices, receipts, and correspondence concerning MTV's Ear to the Ground program.
  - Thorazine performance agreement, 1999 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Al's Bar poem, 1999 September (Box 1, Folder 22)
    This piece was written by Mona Jean Cedar, a poet and sign language interpreter who participated in the following performances at Al's Bar: as a poet performing her own work, as a signing character for the X-rated country music band Honk If Yer Horny, and as a signing go-go dancer for punk rock band Touch Candy.
  - Al's Bar procedures (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This single handwritten sheet of paper details the bar's opening and closing procedures.
  - alsradiophone list (Box 2, Folder 2)
    List includes names of disc jockeys, phone numbers, and names of shows.
  - A.N.T. programs, circa 1987-1990s (Box 2, Folder 3)
    This folder contains the following Al's National Theater (A.N.T.) programs: Going Down Hard, ...And The Jukebox Never Plays The Song You Want To Hear, Mayhem at Mayfield Mall, Mayhem at Mayfield Mall II "The Dirt on Schmeltzer," Mayhem at Mayfield Mall #3 "Mayor Schmeltzer Goes to Washington," Lenin in Love, All the Mothers/The Reversal and the paste-up program for Emmett Till.
  - Loft Maiden materials, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    These folders contain the following materials for Marc Kreisel's two-act musical comedy which was performed at A.N.T.'s open air theater: an annotated script, handwritten notes, programs, press clippings, lyrics, contact sheet, biographies, and correspondence.
  - A.N.T. Traction Ave. project, 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6-12)
    These development folders contain the following A.N.T. materials: Traction Avenue Development Project brochure, Articles of Incorporation, Secretary of State certificates, Board of Directors Minutes, Board resumes, By-Laws, Statement of Purpose, Statement of Activities, and Statement of Fundraising.
  - A.N.T. scripts, undated, 1968, 1989, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
    These folders include scripts for The Story, Voit Where Prohibited, April 9, 1994, Haunted Cabaret, and Emmett Till. Materials also include Director/Cast Assignments for a 5-Minute Play Festival, two plays by Megan Terry, and a collection of poetry by El Gato Rebelde, Andres Carranza entitled, The Ghost of Criminal Past.
  - A.N.T. photographs, circa 1990s (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
    Photographs include color stills of the Lenin in Love cast and black and white casting head shots with annotated biographies attached.
  - A.N.T. ephemera (Box 2, Folder 18)
    One "Mom on Stage" index card.
  - Rolodexes, circa 1976-2001 (Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6)
    Four card indexes which include names, addresses, and telephone numbers.
  - Al's Bar desk calendars, 1996-2000 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
    Five desk calendars include names, numbers, set times, and band lineups.
- Publicity materials, 1978-2003
  Publicity materials include press releases, flyers, photographs, advertisements, one sheets, posters, and clippings.
  - Clippings, 1978-2003 (Box 8, Folder 1-18)
    Marc Kreisel's pen name is I.W. Greenberg or Irene Wint Greenberg. According to Rachel Kreisel, Wint is Marc's maternal grandmother's maiden name and his middle name.
    Clippings from newspapers and magazines include coverage of events at Al's Bar, Al's National Theater, and the American Gallery.
    Folder 4: This folder contains a Los Angeles Times piece on the February 14, 1987 shut down of Al's Bar and arrest of Marc Kreisel after Los Angeles police and fire marshals raided Al's during a Love Tractor show that attracted more than double the bar's capacity.
    Folder 6: This folder contains two articles on the temporary installation of Dustin Shuler's "Pinned Butterfly" which involved pinning a Cessna 150 aircraft with a 20 foot steel nail to the facade of The American Hotel, multiple American Gallery clippings, and "Art World, LA" reviews by I.W. Greenberg.
    Folder 10: This folder contains Al's National Theater clippings, an A.N.T. flyer for Genet's Deathwatch, and a copy of Al's Newsletter which features the "Ask Al" advice "is not cheap" column.
    Folders 14-16: These folders are A.N.T. publicity files for Scenes From the Buried Life, Emmett Till, and The Hemingway/Dos Passos Wars.
  - Permanent Vacation poster, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Poster for the Al's Bar Los Angeles premiere of Jim Jarmusch's film.
  - American Gallery color scans, circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    This folder contains two color scans, one of which is an image of Dustin Shuler's temporary installation, "Pinned Butterfly," a Cessna 150 aircraft pinned to The American Hotel, a four story brick building, by a 20 foot steel nail.
  - Behavioral Patterns advertisement, 1982 February (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Photocopy of a Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art (L.A.I.C.A.) journal advertisement for The Behavioral Patterns of Los Angeles Art Dealers show at the American Gallery. The advertisement features a "Brilliantly and beautifully executed!" blurb from critic at large, Irene Wint Greenberg.
    A poster for this American Gallery show may be found in Box 10.
    According to Marc Kreisel, this was the first American Gallery show. However, Rachel Kreisel recalls the following as the first American Gallery show: "In 1980 there was a performance festival, "Public Spirit" sponsored by a group of five artists called Highland Art Agents where about 60 artists did performance pieces in and around downtown. Five of the works were done at The American Hotel which housed the American Gallery."
  - The Rough Theatre one sheets, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    An excerpt from Peter Brook's The Empty Space accompanies the A.N.T. mission which states, "Al's National Theatre, since its inception has been a popular theatre: ticket prices are low, performances are raw and it is anti-authoritarian."
  - A.N.T. publicity photos, 1987-1990 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Black and white photographs for playwright Joel Bloom's productions Mayhem at the Mayfield Mall and Showdown in Sonoratown: The Lady Who Stole Hollywood. This folder also contains an A.N.T. contact list and a black and white still from Dennis Hackin's Going Down Hard which was directed by Bloom.
  - A.N.T. one sheets, circa 1992 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Sheets describe A.N.T. from its inception in 1985 as "a non-profit organization for people who want to do theatre - no matter what!" Sheets also describe the creators of A.N.T., include an information number, and a list of productions.
  - A.N.T. flyers, undated (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
    These folders contain flyers for the following productions: Mayhem at the Mayfield Mall, Rough Magic, Ballroom Days, Mayhem at the Mayfield Mall #3: Mayor Schmeltzer Goes to Washington, The Lower Depths, and Women Read Bukowski.
  - A.N.T. press release, 1991 November 16-17 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Two press releases for A.N.T.'s first ever "Public Mural Painting & Hip Hop" event which was held from sunrise until sunset on the street outside the theater.
  - Al's Bar flyers, 1996-1999 (Box 9, Folder 10-16)
    Folder 10: Two flyers created by Raymond Pettibon for shows at Big Sail Gallery and Al's Bar.
    Folder 11: First edition Live at Al's release flyers for the compilation featuring performances by The Spent Idols, Pop Defect, TVTV$, Touchcandy, Snair, Flourescein, Bottom 12, The Humpers, Lutefisk, Texas Terri, Extra Fancy, 1,000 Mona Lisas, and Mother Tongue.
    Folder 12: Flyers feature the following bands: Rocket from the Crypt, Tracy & The Hindenberg Ground Crew, Third Grade Teacher, Lucid Nation, The Murder City Devils, The BellRays, Tadpole, Patsy, Bob Sled, Sluts for Hire, Aztlan Underground, Ollin, The Neptunas, and Tribe 8.
    Folder 13: Flyer for The Downtown Art Fair featuring a projection festival at Al's Bar.
    Folder 14: Flyer for the Al's Bar 20th Anniversary "miracle" featuring Keith Morris' Midget Hand Job, The Urinals, Mike Watt & The Black Gang, Sylvia Juncosa and an unconfirmed Special Guest. This folder also contains two free drink tickets signed by Al.
    Folder 15: Six postcards featuring Al's Bar women's room art by becca and promoting Happy Hour Blues with Jake LaBotz.
    Folder 16: Original artwork for flyers featuring Velouria, The Negro Problem, The Vinaigrettes and flyers designed by Dirk Vermin featuring The Hail Marys, The Vermin, The Neptunas, and The Pomeranians. This folder also contains two layouts for V.I.P. Club Passes.
  - Al's Bar t-shirt art, circa 1996 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    Art work includes designs for the following t-shirts: Tip or Die (Brick), Tip or Die (crux), Line Between..., What a Dive pocket T, and Dirk Vermin Fox. This folder also contains a transparency design for The Silverlake Area Militia: Delete, Erase, Undo.
  - Al's Bar press releases, 1986 July, 2001 October 4 (Box 9, Folder 18-19)
    Folder 18: Grasp The Beams: Feel The Strength press release for Steel Erection Month structural renovation.
    Folder 19: Press releases for Dedication Ceremony: The Al's Bar Collection at Highways. This release includes Marc Kreisel's purpose for Al's Bar as a support system for the arts which illuminates The Al's Bar Collection as an example of this process. Some of the artists in the collection who displayed work for the exhibition include John Valadez, Paul Dillon, Maura Sheehan, Merwin Belin, Jack Barth, Ron Linden, Monique Safford, and Katy Crowe.
  - Posters, 1982, 1998, 2000, undated (Box 10)
    Posters include The Behavioral Patterns Of...at The American Gallery, Halloween Night 1998 at Al's Bar designed by John E. Miner, Terry Allen vs. Himself Grudge Match at Al's Bar, Here Lies Popdefect R.I.P. at Al's Bar, A CD Record Release Party for Third Grade Teacher at Al's Bar, The Hail Marys designed by Toast and John E. Miner, Al's Bar New Year's Eve designed by becca and Rolo Castillo, and an Abraham Lincoln John E. Miner design signed by Miner for an Al's Bar show featuring The Homebillies, The Shakedown, Steer Jockey, and Masher.
- Correspondence, circa 1981-2004
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically and includes letters, invitations, notes, postcards, electronic mail printouts, facsimiles, mailing lists, press lists, and stationery.
  - Debbie Drooze letter, February 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    According to Rachel Kreisel, Debbie Drooze booked the bar between 1983 and 1986. Drooze also advocated on behalf of the bar to the City's building and safety unit to try to get the capacity changed. Kreisel recounts, "The bar was only allowed 49 people and that made it impossible for the bands or the bar to make a living."
    Thank you letter addressed to Marc Kreisel for a New Year's Eve show at Al's Bar in which she closes with words from her Jewish granny, "Oy! So why don't you fix the place a'ready!"
  - The Outlaw Tony West letter, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Letter to Al's Bar in which the Outlaw Tony West from Freak Machine states, "Our friends Maple Street and a growing number of bands have joined our boycott of your club."
  - Young Turks Night invitations, 1981 May 7-14 (Box 11, Folder 3-5)
    Invitations and RSVPs for the last annual Young Turks Night at Al's Bar, also known as The Golden Turkey Awards.
  - John Clellon Holmes letter, 1985 August 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Photocopy of a letter to Michael Lucchisi and Suzanne Averitt.
  - Cultural Affairs correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 11, Folder 7-8)
    In addition to City of Los Angeles Cultural Affairs Commission correspondence concerning a Cultural Grant Contract, these folders include the contract between Al's National Theater and the City as well as amendments signed by Mayor Tom Bradley.
  - Mary Alvarado letter, 1991 February 3 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    Letter from Alvarado, the west coast representative for Stage Two theater company, requesting A.N.T. as a venue for the west coast premiere of La Loma.
  - City of Los Angeles correspondence, 1991 May 6 and October 22 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    This folder contains a letter from Mayor Tom Bradley inviting Al's National Theater to the second Los Angeles seminar on theater and a letter from the Cultural Affairs Department expressing support for A.N.T.'s street art crew Mural Project.
  - A.N.T. note, 1991 August 15 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    A note to Marc from a legal expert concerning the adherence to ethical standards.
  - A.N.T. fax, 1992 Mach 23 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    This facsimile consists of a list of A.N.T. productions.
  - A.N.T. donor letters, 1993-1995 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    Thank you letters addressed to individuals and companies who made donations.
  - A.N.T. Director letter, 1994 December (Box 11, Folder 14)
    Correspondence of congratulations from A.N.T. Director Marc Kreisel to Joel Newman on winning the Al's National Theater Grant for his film project, This Old Man.
  - L.A. County Parking letters, 1994-1995 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    Correspondence concerning A.N.T. use of L.A. County parking lots.